# ALEXIS MARCHAND

address DPMMS, Centre for Mathematical Sciences, Wilberforce Road, Cambridge CB3 oWB (UK)

email aptm3@cam.ac.uk

website alexis-marchand.github.io

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is in *geometric group theory*, a field concerned with understanding groups — algebraic structures encoding the symmetries of mathematical objects — by studying their actions on geometric spaces. I am particularly interested in understanding connections between group-theoretical structure and *non-positive curvature*.

**Keywords**: stable commutator length, bounded cohomology, quasimorphisms, topology of surfaces, hyperbolicity, CAT(0) cube complexes, group rings, free group automorphisms.

## **EMPLOYMENT**

2024-25 JSPS Postdoctoral Fellow for Research in Japan  $\cdot$  Kyoto University

Mentor: Koji Fujiwara

## EDUCATION

2021-24 Ph.D. in Pure Mathematics · *University of Cambridge* 

Thesis: Computations and lower bounds for scl and the relative Gromov seminorm Supervisor: Henry Wilton

2017-21 Dipl. ENS · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

2020-21 M.Sc. in Mathematics · *Université Grenoble Alpes* 

Mention Très Bien

Thesis: Automorphismes extérieurs de produits libres : revêtements abéliens

caractéristiques et représentations libres

Supervisor: François Dahmani

2019-20 M.A.St. in Mathematics · *University of Cambridge* 

Pass with Merit

Essay: Rigidity Theorems for Hyperbolic Groups

Supervisor: Henry Wilton

2017-19 B.Sc. in Mathematics · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

Research internships:

- Topology of complex affine varieties, with Hossein Movasati in IMPA, Rio de Janeiro (2019)
- Geometry of Coxeter groups, with CATERINA CAMPAGNOLO in KIT, Karlsruhe (2018)

#### ACCEPTED PAPERS

- [1] Alexis Marchand, From letter-quasimorphisms to angle structures and spectral gaps for scl, 2024. *Israel J. Math.* (to appear). arXiv:2402.13856
- [2] Alexis Marchand, Bavard duality for the relative Gromov seminorm, 2023. *Enseign. Math.* (to appear). arXiv:2305.02149
- [3] Alexis Marchand, Isometric embeddings of surfaces for scl, 2023. *Groups Geom. Dyn.* (to appear). arXiv:2302.04133
- [4] Alexis Marchand, Free representations of outer automorphism groups of free products via characteristic abelian coverings, *J. Group Theory* **26** (2023), no. 2, 399-420.

DOI:10.1515/jgth-2021-0154  $\cdot$  arXiv:2107.11230

## **EXPOSITORY ARTICLES**

- [5] Alexis Marchand, Makers of patterns: from Escher to Coxeter, Eureka 66 (2020).
- [6] Alexis Marchand, Géométrie des groupes et courbure négative, Journal de Mathématiques des Élèves de l'ENS de Lyon IV (2020).

# TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2021-24 Undergraduate supervisions · Trinity College & Peterhouse College, Cambridge

- Analysis & Topology (IB) 46 contact hours
- Geometry (IB) 34 contact hours
- Linear Algebra (IB) 16 contact hours
- Riemann Surfaces (II) 31 contact hours
- Part III examples classes · *University of Cambridge*

Teaching assistant for Geometric Group Theory — 8 contact hours

2022-23 Admissions interviews · Christ's College, Cambridge

Co-interviewer for undergraduate admissions in mathematics

2021-23 Part III drop-in sessions · *University of Cambridge* 

Drop-in session leader for Group Cohomology, Mapping Class Groups

2019-20 School tutoring · Stimulus, Cambridge

Volunteer tutor in mathematics in secondary schools

2018-19 Colles · Lycée Aux Lazaristes, Lyon

Oral examiner in mathematics for first-year students in a preparatory class — 44 contact hours

2017-21 French as a foreign language · *ItinérENS*, *Lyon* 

Volunteer teacher of French classes for refugees and migrants — more than 100 contact hours

#### ORGANISATIONAL EXPERIENCE

<sup>2023-24</sup> Junior geometry seminar · *University of Cambridge* 

Co-organiser of the graduate students' seminar in geometry

2023-24 BA computing · Trinity College, Cambridge

MCR committee member in charge of: the MCR's website, mailing list, elections, lunchtime seminars, etc.

2022 Reading seminar · *University of Cambridge* 

Organiser of a reading seminar on generalisations of hyperbolic groups

#### AWARDS

<sup>2023</sup> Smith–Knight & Rayleigh–Knight prize · *University of Cambridge* 

Grade 3, for the essay Isometric embeddings of surfaces for scl

2021 EPSRC PhD studentship · University of Cambridge

Three-year studentship funded by the Engineering & Physical Sciences Research Council

2017 ENS studentship · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

Four-year studentship with civil servant status funded by the French government

## INVITED TALKS

Nov. 2024 First MMS workshop for young researchers · Kyoto University

May 2024 Seminari dei baby geometri · Università di Pisa / Scuola Normale Superiore

Apr. 2024 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial

volume · Online

Apr. 2024 Geometry and geometric analysis seminar · Purdue University (online)

Mar. 2024 Geometric group theory seminar · University of Oxford

Dec. 2023 Bristol junior geometry seminar · University of Bristol

Jun. 2023 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial

volume · Online

*Apr.* 2023 Methusalem junior seminar · KU Leuven

Mar. 2023 Geometry graduate colloquium · ETH Zürich

Feb. 2023 Junior topology & group theory seminar · University of Oxford

Feb. 2023 Geometric group theory seminar · University of Cambridge

Jan. 2023 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial

volume · Online

Jun. 2022 Séminaire compréhensible · Université Grenoble Alpes

Apr. 2022 Séminaire des doctorants de St-Charles · Aix-Marseille Université

## CONFERENCES ATTENDED

- Apr. 2024 Groups, topology, & applications Gran Bilbao · Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea
- Mar. 2024 Topological & homological methods in group theory · Universität Bielefeld
- Feb. 2024 GAGTA · CIRM, Marseille

Contributed talk & poster

- Jul. 2023 Postgraduate group theory conference · Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh Contributed talk
- May 2023 Geometry of subgroups · CRM, Montréal
- Jan. 2023 LMS regional meeting · University of Southampton
  Contributed poster
- Sep. 2022 Recent advances in bounded cohomology · Universität Regensburg
- Jun. 2022 Hyperbolic groups and their generalisations · IHP, Paris
- *Apr.* 2022 Mapping class groups and Out  $(F_n)$  · *IHP, Paris*
- Apr. 2022 Groups acting on fractals · CIRM, Marseille
- Feb. 2022 Workshop on finiteness properties · KIT, Karlsruhe

# LANGUAGES

French	Native speaker	Portuguese	Advanced (B2)
English	Fluent (C2). Passed the CAE	Russian	Intermediate (B1)
GERMAN	Advanced (B2)	Japanese	Elementary (A2)

August 12, 2024